<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<catalogue>

  <painting>
           <id>01</id>
           <title>Madame Roulin and Her Baby</title>
           <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
           <date>1888</date>
           <description>This vigorously painted portrait of Augustine Roulin and her infant daughter, Marcelle, is one of Van Gogh’s many evocative renderings of the Roulin family, undertaken some six months after the artist relocated from Paris to Arles. Van Gogh painted the entire family of the local postman Joseph Roulin. Here, the chubbycheeked infant is the focus of the enterprise. Her heightened expression in thickly painted brushwork suggests that the baby may have posed for van Gogh, swaddled in her mother’s embrace. Augustine Roulin, by contrast, is an abbreviated presence.</description> 
           <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
           <dimensions>25x20</dimensions>
           <collection>Robert Lehman Collection</collection>    
           <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/459123</url>
 </painting>

  <painting>
           <id>02</id>
           <title>Shoes</title>
           <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
           <date>1888</date>
           <description>Van Gogh painted several still lifes of shoes or boots during his Paris period. This picture, painted later, in Arles, evinces a unique return to the earlier motif. However, here Van Gogh has placed the shoes within a specific spatial context: namely, the red-tile floor of the Yellow House. Not only may we identify the setting, but perhaps the owner of the shoes as well. It has been suggested that this "still life of old peasants' shoes" may have been those of Patience Escalier, whose portrait Van Gogh executed around the same time, late summer 1888.</description> 
           <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
           <dimensions>18x21</dimensions>
           <collection>Robert Lehman Collection</collection>    
           <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436533</url>
 </painting>  
    
 <painting>
          <id>03</id>
          <title>Shoes</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1888</date>
          <description>Van Gogh painted several still lifes of shoes or boots during his Paris period. This picture, painted later, in Arles, evinces a unique return to the earlier motif. However, here Van Gogh has placed the shoes within a specific spatial context: namely, the red-tile floor of the Yellow House. Not only may we identify the setting, but perhaps the owner of the shoes as well. It has been suggested that this "still life of old peasants' shoes" may have been those of Patience Escalier, whose portrait Van Gogh executed around the same time, late summer 1888.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>18x21</dimensions>
          <collection>Purchase, The Annenberg Foundation Gift</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436533</url>
 </painting>  
    
 <painting>
          <id>04</id>
          <title>Irises</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1890</date>
          <description>In May 1890, just before he checked himself out of the asylum at Saint-Rémy, Van Gogh painted four exuberant bouquets of spring flowers, the only still lifes of any ambition he had undertaken during his yearlong stay: two of irises, two of roses, in contrasting color schemes and formats. In the Museum’s Irises he sought a “harmonious and soft” effect by placing the “violet” flowers against a “pink background,” which have since faded owing to his use of fugitive red pigments.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>29x36</dimensions>
          <collection>Gift of Adele R. Levy</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436528</url> 
 </painting>  
    
  <painting>
           <id>05</id>
           <title>Wheat Field with Cypresses</title>
           <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
           <date>1889</date>
           <description>Cypresses gained ground in Van Gogh’s work by late June 1889 when he resolved to devote one of his first series in Saint-Rémy to the towering trees. Distinctive for their rich impasto, his exuberant on-the-spot studies include the Met’s close-up vertical view of cypresses (49.30) and this majestic horizontal composition, which he illustrated in reed-pen drawings sent to his brother on July 2.</description> 
           <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
           <dimensions>28x36</dimensions>
           <collection>The Annenberg Foundation Gift</collection>    
           <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436535</url>   
 </painting>    
    
  <painting>
           <id>06</id>
           <title>Self-Portrait with a Straw Hat</title>
           <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
           <date>1887</date>
           <description>Van Gogh produced more than twenty self-portraits during his Parisian sojourn (1886–88). Short of funds but determined nevertheless to hone his skills as a figure painter, he became his own best sitter: "I purposely bought a good enough mirror to work from myself, for want of a model." This picture, which shows the artist's awareness of Neo-Impressionist technique and color theory, is one of several that are painted on the reverse of an earlier peasant study.</description> 
           <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
           <dimensions>16x12</dimensions>
           <collection>Bequest of Miss Adelaide Milton de Groot</collection>    
           <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436532</url>
 </painting>
    
  <painting>
          <id>07</id>
          <title>L'Arlésienne: Madame Joseph-Michel Ginoux (Marie Julien, 1848–1911)</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1888-1889</date>
          <description>While in Arles, Van Gogh painted two very similar portraits of Marie Ginoux, the proprietress of the Café de la Gare, wearing the regional costume of the legendary dark-haired beauties of Arles. The first version, which he described in a letter of November 1888 as "an Arlésienne . . . knocked off in one hour," must be the more thinly and summarily executed portrait in the Musée d'Orsay, Paris. In it a parasol and gloves lie on the table instead of books. This portrait belonged to the sitter until she sold it in 1895.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>36x29</dimensions>
          <collection>Bequest of Sam A. Lewisohn</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436529</url>    
</painting>
    
 <painting>
          <id>08</id>
          <title>Road in Etten</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1881</date>
          <description>In 1881 van Gogh briefly resided in Etten, where he produced a number of drawings of local peasants and laborers performing routine, humble tasks. This masterful work, in which a man with a broom is seen sweeping a street lined with pollard willows, is a characteristic example.</description> 
          <medium>Chalk, pencil, pastel, watercolor. Underdrawing in pen and brown ink.</medium>
          <dimensions>15x22</dimensions>
          <collection>Robert Lehman Collection</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/459193</url>     
</painting>
    
 <painting>
          <id>09</id>
          <title>First Steps, after Millet</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1890</date>
          <description>In fall and winter 1889–90, while a voluntary patient at the asylum in Saint-Rémy, Van Gogh painted twenty-one copies after Millet, an artist he greatly admired. He considered his copies "translations" akin to a musician's interpretation of a composer's work. He let the black-and-white images—whether prints, reproductions, or, as here, a photograph that his brother, Theo, had sent—pose "as a subject," then he would "improvise color on it." For this work of January 1890, Van Gogh squared-up a photograph of Millet's First Steps and transferred it to the canvas.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>28x35</dimensions>
          <collection>Gift of George N. and Helen M. Richar</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436526</url> 
</painting> 
      
 <painting>
          <id>10</id>
          <title>The Potato Peeler</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1885</date>
          <description>This painting from February/March 1885, with its restricted palette of dark tones, coarse facture, and blocky drawing, is typical of the works Van Gogh painted in Nuenen the year before he left Holland for France. His peasant studies of 1885 culminated in his first important painting, The Potato Eaters (Van Gogh Museum, Amsterdam).</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>16x12</dimensions>
          <collection>Bequest of Miss Adelaide Milton de Groot</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/438722</url>   
</painting>   

 <painting>
          <id>11</id>
          <title>La Berceuse (Woman Rocking a Cradle; Augustine-Alix Pellicot Roulin, 1851–1930)</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1889</date>
          <description>Of the five versions of Van Gogh’s portrait of Augustine Roulin, wife of his friend the postmaster of Arles, the present canvas is the one the sitter chose for herself. Van Gogh remarked that "she had a good eye and took the best." He began the portraits just before his breakdown in Arles, in December 1888, and completed them in early 1889, calling them "La Berceuse," meaning "lullaby, or woman who rocks the cradle," indicated by the rope held in the sitter’s hand, which is attached to the unseen cradle.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>36x29</dimensions>
          <collection>The Walter H. and Leonore Annenberg Collection</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/437984</url>  
</painting>    
    
 <painting>
          <id>12</id>
          <title>Corridor in the Asylum</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1889</date>
          <description>This haunting view of a sharply receding corridor is the artist's most powerful depiction of the asylum of Saint-Paul-de-Mausole in St. Rémy, where he spent twelve months near the end of his life and where he painted the Museum's oils of olive groves, cypresses, roses, and irises.</description> 
          <medium>Oil color and essence over black chalk on pink laid ("Ingres") paper</medium>
          <dimensions>25x19</dimensions>
          <collection>Bequest of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/336327</url>    
</painting>
    
 <painting>
          <id>13</id>
          <title>The Flowering Orchard</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1888</date>
          <description>The arrival of spring in Arles in 1888 found Van Gogh "in a fury of work." As he wrote to his brother Theo, "the trees are in blossom and I would like to do a Provençal orchard of tremendous gaiety." Between late March and late April, the artist dedicated fourteen canvases to the subject, working in a range of sizes, formats, and styles. This composition, dominated by the angular, elongated branches of the budding trees, attests to Van Gogh’s admiration for Japanese prints. His inclusion of the scythe and rake makes this one of only two orchard paintings to hint at a human presence.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>28x21</dimensions>
          <collection>The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Ittleson Jr. Purchase Fund</collection>     
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/336327</url>        
</painting>
    
 <painting>
          <id>14</id>
          <title>Oleanders</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1888</date>
          <description>For Van Gogh, oleanders were joyous, life-affirming flowers that bloomed "inexhaustibly" and were always "putting out strong new shoots." In this painting of August 1888 the flowers fill a majolica jug that the artist used for other still lifes made in Arles. They are symbolically juxtaposed with Émile Zola's La joie de vivre, a novel that Van Gogh had placed in contrast to an open Bible in a Nuenen still life of 1885.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>23x29</dimensions>
          <collection>Gift of Mr. and Mrs. John L. Loeb</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436530</url>    
</painting>
    
 <painting>
          <id>15</id>
          <title>Peasant Woman Cooking by a Fireplace</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1885</date>
          <description>This work was made in Nuenen in late spring 1885, just after Van Gogh completed The Potato Eaters (Van Gogh Museum, Amsterdam), in the same dark hues that reminded the artist of "green soap" or "a really dusty potato, unpeeled of course." Van Gogh was "convinced that in the long run it produces better results to paint [peasants] in their coarseness than to introduce conventional sweetness… If a peasant painting smells of bacon, smoke, potato steam—fine—that’s not unhealthy—if a stable smells of manure—very well, that’s what a stable’s for."</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>17x15</dimensions>
          <collection>Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Mortimer Hays</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436531</url>    
</painting>    
    
 <painting>
          <id>16</id>
          <title>Sunflowers</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1887</date>
          <description>Van Gogh painted four still lifes of sunflowers in Paris in late summer 1887. There is an oil sketch for this picture (Van Gogh Museum, Amsterdam) as well as another painting of two sunflowers also signed and dated 1887 (Kunstmuseum Bern), and a larger canvas showing four sunflower heads</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>17x24</dimensions>
          <collection>Rogers Fund</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436524</url>   
</painting>    
    
 <painting>
          <id>17</id>
          <title>The Zouave</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1888</date>
          <description>During a spell of torrential rain that interrupted his harvest series (June 20–24), Van Gogh made his first real effort at portraiture in Arles. Two days into his campaign, he announced to Theo: "I have a model at last—a Zouave—a boy with a small face, a bull neck, and the eye of the tiger." The present work served as a color study for his bust-length portrait of the dashing young soldier. In the oil painting, Van Gogh heightened the "savage combination of incongruous tones," fleshed out the character's likeness, and placed him in a convincing setting. That July he sent the watercolor, with dedicatory inscription, to his "comrade Émile Bernard."</description> 
          <medium>Reed pen and brown ink, wax crayon and watercolor, over graphite; wove paper</medium>
          <dimensions>12x9</dimensions>
          <collection>Gift of Emanie Philips</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/335536</url>      
</painting>    
    
 <painting>
          <id>18</id>
          <title>Women Picking Olives</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1889</date>
          <description>At the end of 1889, Van Gogh painted three versions of this picture. He described the first as a study from nature "more colored with more solemn tones" (private collection) and the second as a studio rendition in a "very discreet range" of colors.</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>28x36</dimensions>
          <collection>The Walter H. and Leonore Annenberg Collection</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/436536</url> 
</painting>   
    
 <painting>
          <id>19</id>
          <title>Olive Trees</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1889</date>
          <description>This is one of five pictures of olive orchards that Van Gogh made in November 1889. Painted directly from nature but animated by Seurat-like stippling and stylized passages of broken color, these works responded to recent compositions by Paul Gauguin and Émile Bernard. "What I’ve done is a rather harsh and coarse realism beside their abstractions," Van Gogh observed, "but it will nevertheless impart a rustic note, and will smell of the soil."</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>25x36</dimensions>
          <collection>The Walter H. and Leonore Annenberg Collection</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/437998</url>
</painting>    
    
 <painting>
          <id>20</id>
          <title>Cypresses</title>
          <artist>Vincent van Gogh </artist>
          <date>1889</date>
          <description>Cypresses was painted in late June 1889, shortly after Van Gogh began his yearlong stay at the asylum in Saint-Rémy. The subject, which he found "beautiful as regards lines and proportions, like an Egyptian obelisk," both captivated and challenged the artist: "It’s the dark patch in a sun-drenched landscape, but it’s one of the most interesting dark notes, the most difficult to hit off exactly that I can imagine."</description> 
          <medium>Oil on canvas</medium>
          <dimensions>36x29</dimensions>
          <collection>Rogers Fund</collection>    
          <url>https://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/437980</url> 
 </painting>  

</catalogue>    